A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Public Affairs Program, Office Files of William Pincus FA1375
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Public Affairs Program, Office Files of William Pincus
1954-1967
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Pincus, William (1920-2014)
FA1375
1.56 Cubic Feet 4 document boxes: 2 legal size boxes, 1 half-legal size box, and 1 letter box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in one accession in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:073.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of three series.
Original order was maintained.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Correspondence, 1957-1966
Series 2. Subject files, 1957-1966
Series 3. Grant files, 1954-1967
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the office files William Pincus created and maintained between 1957 and 1966 when he worked in the Ford Foundation's Public Affairs Program. The collection is comprised of three series with each series containing one type of record. These record types include correspondence, subject files, and grant files.
Files in the collection demonstrate Pincus' work managing grants and supporting projects related to legal education, civil service, legal and constitutional studies, public policy, legal services, and criminal justice.
In addition to correspondence, the collection contains notes, drafts, reports, proposals, program action records, newspaper clippings, press releases, newsletters, publications, and a photograph.
Ford Foundation; Civil service; Criminal justice, Administration of; Law --Study and teaching; Legal aid; Legal services; Public policy
- Correspondence, 1957-1966; 1; .24 Cubic Feet 1 half document box: 1 half-legal size box
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the correspondence William Pincus created and maintained when he worked in the Ford Foundation's Public Affairs Program. It spans Pincus' entire tenure in the Public Affairs Program which lasted from 1957 to 1966. The files include both Pincus' outgoing and incoming correspondence. The correspondence is ordered in reverse chronological order.
  The correspondence documents various aspects of Pincus' focus at the Ford Foundation, including legal education, legal aid and services, public policy, and criminal justice.
  - 1966 correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - 1957-1965 correspondence (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Subject files, 1957-1966; 2; .24 Cubic Feet 1 half document box: 1 half-legal size box
  This series contains a small number of subject files William Pincus created and maintained when he worked in the Ford Foundation's Public Affairs Program.
  The files document several aspects of Pincus' focus in the Public Affairs Program including public policy, government, criminal justice, and civil service.
  - The Brookings Institution Governmental Studies - Program of research and education, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Citizens Union of the City of New York - General materials and George Hallett, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - United States Civil Service Commission, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Grant files, 1954-1967; 3; 1.09 Cubic Feet 3 document boxes: 1 legal size, 1 half-legal size, and 1 letter size box
  This series documents William Pincus' management of various grants for the Ford Foundation's Public Affairs Program between the 1950s and 1960s. The files are ordered by the date the Foundation issued the grants. These dates are represented in the first two digits of the grants' Program Action numbers which are included on every file title in the series (ex. 55-25).
  The files contain correspondence, program action records, and reports that document grant approvals, modifications, extensions, progress, and products. Grants concern legal education, training and development programs for Federal and public workers, and constitutional studies. The grants supported projects like internships, conferences, research, and publications. The Ford Foundation gave the grants to law schools and other universities, legal associations, and nonprofit organizations.
  - National Legal Aid and Defender Association (NLADA) (53-25, See also 59-516), 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Harvard University Law School - International legal studies (55-13), 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Philip W. Buck, Stanford University (55-30), 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Bar Foundation (ABF) - Survey of administration of criminal justice in the United States (55-53 and 55-33B), 1957-1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - University of Chicago Law School - Law and behavioral science program (55-122), 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Brookings Institution - Federal executives conference program (55-160), 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Yale University Law School - Teacher training and international legal studies (55-222), 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - National Municipal League - General support (55-225 and 55-225A, see also 57-270), 1954-1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Institute of International Education (IIE) - Travel and study awards (56-14), 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - American Society for Public Administration (ASPA) (56-15), 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Harvard University Law School - Graduate Fellowships for Law Teaching (56-208), 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Regional Plan Association (RPA) (56-210), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Association of American Law Schools (AALS) - Study of resources for American law education (57-4), 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Washington State Research Council - Interim Legislative Conference (57–6), 1957-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - American Political Science Association (ASPA) - Congressional Fellowship Program (57-20, 57-20A, 57-20B, 57-20C), 1957-1967 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - University of California Berkeley - Legislative internship program (57-21), 1957-1966 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - American Heritage Foundation (57-147), 1958-1963; File contains a still image. The still image is a photograph. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    The photograph shows the American Heritage Foundation Board Chairman, General Sarnoff, and President, John C. Cornelius, presenting the Foundation Award for Citizenship to Paul Butler (Democratic National Chairman) and Meade Alcorn (Republican National Chairman). The photograph was taken by Thomas H. Murtaugh. There is a caption describing the content of the photograph.
  - Fair Campaign Practices Committee, Inc. (57-188, also includes 60-1128), 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - University of Chicago - Summer Institute of Executive Development for Top Level Federal Administrators (57-241 and 57-241B), 1957-1961 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Rutgers University - Study of selected state constitutional problems (57-243 and 57-243A), 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Association of American Law Schools (AALS) - Conference educating lawyers (57-245, also 56-50), 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Columbia University - Research and publication in state legal and constitutional materials (57-269), 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - National Municipal League - State Constitutional Studies Program research and publication (57-270), 1957-1965 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - University of Chicago - Executive development program for public and civic organization personnel (57-271), 1957-1964 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - New York University - Executive Development Program for the City of New York and Metropolitan Area (57-272), 1957-1964 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - West Virginia University - Pre-legislative conference (57-306), 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - West Virginia University - Research and study in political science (57-365), 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Princeton University - Publication of the Thomas Jefferson papers (57-410), 1957-1962 (Box 4, Folder 36)